Guide to the William Broyles, Jr. Papers
The Wittliff Collections
- Television Projects - Produced, 1987-1993
  - J.F.K.: Reckless Youth, 1993 (Box 180-183)
    In 1993, Broyles adapted the Nigel Hamilton novel, J.F.K.: Reckless Youth for television. The mini-series of the same names follows the future president during his formative first thirty years and stars Patrick Dempsey as the young J.F.K. Notebooks, script drafts, and correspondence document Broyles' work on the teleplay.
- Television Projects - Unproduced, 1991-1993 (Box 183-189)
  Between 1991 and 1993, Broyles worked on developing a handful of television projects that were never produced. Included are South Central, Hot on the Trail, and Adventure, Inc. / Angels Camp. This series includes research files, story development, scripts, correspondence, and other materials relating to the various projects.
- Film Projects - Produced, 1993-2002
  In 1993, Broyles turned his attention from television projects to writing feature films. This series includes materials relating to the following films: Apollo 13 (1995), Entrapment (1999), Cast Away (2000), Planet of the Apes (2001), and Unfaithful (2002). Broyles' work on various projects often overlapped, so this series is arranged chronologically according to the year each film was released.
  - Apollo 13, 1993-1996, 2001 (Box 190-198)
    Broyles shares his first major motion picture writing credits with former Texas Monthly writer, Al Reinert. Based loosely upon Apollo 13 astronaut Jim Lovell's novel Lost Moon co-written with Jeffrey Kluger, the 1995 film marks Broyles' first collaboration with director Ron Howard.
    The Apollo 13 series is arranged chronologically, reflecting the development of the project. The first subseries, correspondence (box 190), includes letters between Broyles and Michael Bostick, Broyles' assistant, Sheila Gallion, James Lovell, and Al Reinert. The next four subseries: research, notes, story development, and scripts (boxes 190-195), highlight Broyles and Reinert's writing process. Of note within the research files are the book proposal and typescript of Lost Moon. The scripts subseries includes multiple revisions of each draft of the screenplay. Following the scripts, there are a number of files relating to Broyles' and Reinert's WGA writers credit arbitration (boxes 195-196) that provide insight into the complex legalities of the craft.
    The final subseries of the Apollo 13 materials are production files, publicity materials, and awards. Broyles and Reinert were nominated for an Academy Award for their work, as well as a Golden Globe, a Pen Center USA West Literary Award, and a Writers Guild Award. Of interest in the awards subseries is a videotaped message of congratulations from Ron Howard (box 197), a celebratory bottle of champagne, and numerous letters of congratulations.
  - Entrapment, 1997-1999 (Box 199-203)
    In 1998, Broyles was hired to rewrite the Y2K caper, Entrapment, starring Sean Connery and Catherine Zeta Jones. Broyles shares writing credits with Ron Bass and Don Macpherson, both of whom worked on earlier versions of the screenplay. Correspondence, research, scripts (including drafts by Bass and Macpherson), production materials, and videocassettes document Broyles' contribution to the film.
  - Cast Away, 1994-2001, undated (Box 204-227)
    The largest amount of material within the produced films series relates to Broyles's work on Cast Away. Broyles had the idea for the original film about a FedEx delivery driver stranded on a deserted island, and he saw it through from start to finish. This series of material provides valuable insight into the process of developing and writing an original motion picture. The 2000 film was produced by Ron Howard and Brian Grazer, directed by Robert Zemeckis, and stars Tom Hanks. Broyles's letters and memos with these individuals can be found within the correspondence series.
    The bulk of the Cast Away series is comprised of scripts. Broyles's entire writing process is evident from his early notes to the final shooting script. In all, there are over one hundred revised versions of the script. Many contain or refer to notes by Broyles, Sheila Gallien, Tom Hanks, and Robert Zemeckis. Additional materials within the Cast Away series are production files on art, casting, and schedules; publicity records, awards, and artifacts including a promotional Wilson volleyball and a coconut tree bark mask.
  - Planet of the Apes, 1968; 1988-1989; 1999-2001 (Box 228-232)
    Broyles shares writing credits on the 2001 Tim Burton film, Planet of the Apes. The film is based on the Pierre Boule novel of the same name, and stars Mark Wahlberg, Tim Roth, and Helena Bonham Carter. Correspondence, research materials (including copies of Boule's novel and previous Apes films), scripts, and writers credit arbitration files, and publicity materials document Broyles's contribution to the film.
  - Unfaithful, 2000-2001 (Box 233)
    This small series includes correspondence, notes, and writers arbitration materials relating to Broyles's work on the 2002 film, Unfaithful, starring Diane Lane and Richard Gere.
- Film Projects - Unproduced, 1987-1999
  This series contains research materials, notes, scripts, and correspondence for a number of film projects that have not been produced. Arranged alphabetically by working title, these projects include: "Baa Baa Black Sheep", "Earth Angel" (a.k.a. "Huey and the War Lover"), "Hard Rock: There Are No limits," "R&R," "Terrible Beauty: Stories From a War," and an untitled baseball project.
  - "Baa Baa Black Sheep", 1997-1999 (Box 233)
  - "Earth Angel" [a.k.a. Huey and the War Lovers], undated (Box 234-235)
  - "Hard Rock: There are no Limits", 1987, undated (Box 235)
  - "R & R", 1989-1991, undated (Box 236-241)
  - "Terrible Beauty: Stories from a War", 1986 (Box 241)
  - Untitled baseball project, 1998-1999 (Box 241)
- Writings by Others, 1982-1990, undated (Box 242-246)
  This series contains a number of television and motion picture scripts by other writers. Many were sent as writing samples to Broyles in his role of producer for China Beach and Under Cover. Some of the television projects represented are 21 Jump Street, Cagney and Lacey, Law and Order, Miami Vice, and Thirty-Something.
- Videocassettes, 1988-1991, undated (Box 247-264)
  This series includes VHS cassettes of China Beach and Under Cover episodes, a few dailies from these shows, as well as some ¾ inch NTSC cassettes.